http://youtu.be/gGtm9PN44Uo
http://youtu.be/gGtm9PN44Uo Tung Dinh _ VGU
JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's look at the software needed to initialize the UART.
Giờ ta quan sát software để khởi tạo UART
We're going to execute it once to turn it on.
Ta sẽ chạy nó mỗi lần bật lên
There are three things that we have to do.
Có 3 thứ ta cần làm
First, we have to select which UART to use.
Đầu tiên, ta phải chọn sử dụng UART nào
There are eight of them, and we're going to use UART1.
Có 8 UART, ta chọn UART1
So we'll turn on the clock for UART1.
Vậy, ta bật clock cho UART1
And you notice, we're going to configure the registers for UART1.
Chú ý, ta sẽ chỉnh register cho UART1
The second we have to do is select which pins to use,
Thứ hai, ta phải chọn pins
and we're going to use two of the pins here in port C to implement our UART.
ta chọn 2 pins này ở portC
So we'll turn on the clock for port C, and then we
Ta sẽ bật clock cho portC
will set the alternative function register for bits PC5 and PC4.
rồi set register cho bits PC5 và PC4
They will become our UART bits.
Chúng sẽ trở thành UART bits
We have to enable those pins as digital outputs or inputs--
Ta sẽ kích hoạt những pins này thành digital outputs hoặc inputs
again, on PC5 and 4.
trên PC5 và PC4
And the last is-- These two bits in the PCTL register
Cuối cùng là 2 bits trong register PCTL
are selected to be the alternative function, which is the UART.
được chọn làm chức năng thay thế. là UART
So setting a 22 into these two bits of the PCTL
ta set 22 trong 2 bits của PCTL
will set PC5 and 4 to be UARTs.
sẽ set PC5 và PC4 thành UARTs
And they're not analog, so we'll shut off the analog.
và chúng không phải analog, ta tắt analog đi
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, Jon, do we do anything
Jon, ta có cần làm gì
with the direction register for port C?
với register hướng cho PortC không?
JONATHAN VALVANO: No.
Không cần
Because the UART is fixed, PC5 five will be an output and PC4 will be an input.
Bởi UART thì cố định, PC5 sẽ là output, và PC4 là input
And that's automatically set by selecting it as a UART.
Cái đó tự động set khi chúng là UART
RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
Ok
JONATHAN VALVANO: And the third thing we have to do is set the baud-rate.
Điều thứ 3 ta phải làm là set tốc độ truyền tải
The baud rate set in these two registers.
Nó được set trong 2 registers này
Let's look at the calculation.
Giờ ta quan sát phần tính toán
The calculation is shown here.
ở đây
We'll begin with the bus clock-- which, in this case,
Ta bắt đầu với bus clock,
is going to be 80 megahertz.
ở đây là 80 Mhz
The 16 is a fixed constant-- which will always be 16--
16 là hằng số, luôn luôn là 16
and then here is our input.
và đây là input
We would like to set the baud-rate to 115,200 bits per second.
ta set tốc độ là 115200 bits/s
RAMESH YERRABALLI: This is a standard baud-rate
Đây là tốc độ chuẩn
that is used in communication.
sử dụng trong thông tin liên lạc
JONATHAN VALVANO: And a fast one.
Và nó cũng nhanh nữa
When you calculate it, you get this number here-- 43.40278.
Khi tính toán, ta có 43.40278
We're going to take the 43 and put it right there.
ta lấy 43 và để ở đây
And we're going to take the fraction and create
lấy phần dư
a binary fraction by multiplying by 64.
và tạo 1 phân số nhị phân bằng việc nhân với 64
Again, it's always 64 in this spot.
nó luôn luôn là 64
In this case, we're going to get a quotient of 26.
Trong trường hợp này, ta có 26
And the 26 goes in there.
để ở đây
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So these are the Integer part and the Fractional part
Vậy ta có phần nguyên và phần dư
of the calculation we performed from when we set our desired baud-rate.
của phép tính khi ta set tốc độ ta cần
JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
Chính xác
In summary, there are three things that we're going to do.
Tóm lại, có 3 thứ ta cần làm
First, we're going to turn on the clock for UART1.
Đầu tiên là bật clock cho UART1
Two, we're going to select which pins to use-- in this case, PC5 and 4.
Hai là chọn pins sử dụng, ở đây là PC5 và PC4
And three, we're going to set the baud rate
Và ba, ta sẽ set tốc độ truyền tải
by setting two values into these two registers.
bằng việc set 2 giá trị vào trong 2 registers
RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
O
Once we initialize the UART for transmission and receiving
Khi ta đã khởi tạo UART cho truyền và nhận
on a particular port, we will have to write a device driver
trên 1 port nhất định, ta phải viết driver cho thiết bị
routine for input and output.
dùng cho input và output
The first one we look at is the InChar.
Cái đầu tiên quan tâm là InChar
So the receiver code where we read a input-- .
code nhận, chỗ ta đọc input
This is to read an input character-- which
Dùng để đọc input character
is a 8-bit data that we are receiving.
là 8 bits
If I want to read it, my logic says that I'm
Nếu ta muốn đọc nó, theo logic
going to check a flag-- which is my receiver FIFO empty flag(RXFE).
ta phải check cờ RXFE
If this flag is 1, it tells me that the FIFO is empty,
Nếu cờ là 1, FIFO trống
which means that I have nothing to consume.
nghĩa là ta không còn gì để làm nữa
So I'm going to go back and check again.
Vậy ta quay lại và check lại
And I keep checking till this flag becomes a 0.
Và cứ tiếp tục đến khi chờ bằng 0
So what I'm doing here it is it's saying--
Vậy ta đang làm ở đây
While this flag is not equal to 0-- which means it's equal to 1--
Trong khi cờ khác 0, nghĩa là nó bằng 1
I keep repeating this loop.
Ta vẫn lập lại loop này
So this while loop really has no body, which
Và while loop này không có body
means it's going to repeatedly check it.
nghĩa là nó cứ liên tục check
It is a 1.
It is a 1.
Once it is 0-- which means it's not empty--
Khi nó bằng 0, nghĩa là nó trống
which tells me that there's something to be consumed-- then
nghĩa là ta có thứ để làm
I'm going to read the data.
vậy, ta cứ tiếp tục đọc data
And the way I read the data is by looking
bằng cách nhìn tại
at the data register(UART1_DR_R).
data register (UART1_DR_R)
So the data register will give me the data.
data register sẽ cho ta data
And because it's a 32-bit register, I'm just masking
và bởi nó là register 32-bit, vừa đánh dấu
and I'm only taking the lower 8 bits off it.
và ta chỉ lấy 8 bits dưới
And I'm going to return that to my caller.
và ta sẽ return nó cho caller
So this is my return.
Đây là chỗ return
JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
Đúng rồi
Let's output.
Tới phần output
The output function is also busy-wait synchronization,
Function output là kiểu bận-chờ
and the output function will output one character to the serial port.
và nó sẽ output 1 charater ra serial port
It also will look at a flag.
Nó cũng phụ thuộc vào 1 cờ
The particular flag I'm interested in is the transmit FIFO full flag(TXFF).
Đó là cờ TXFF
And this flag has two states.
Cờ này có 2 trạng thái
If the transmit FIFO flag is equal to a 1,
Nếu FIFO = 1
that means the transfer FIFO is full.
nghĩa là FIFO đầy
And there's no more data, no more place to output.
không còn chỗ để output
So we will wait.
Vậy ta phải chờ
So if the transmitter is busy outputting previous characters,
Vậy nếu nó bận output characters trước
we will wait by going back.
ta phải đợi bằng cách quay lại
If the flag is 0, that means the FIFO is not full.
Nếu cờ = 0, nghĩa là FIFO không đầy
And the device is ready to accept another character.
và thiết bị sẵn sàng nhận charater khác
And when we have that, what we're going to do
Và nếu như vậy,
is we're going to output the next piece of data.
ta sẽ output phần data tiếp theo
We're going to write the next data to the device, and then we'll return.
Ta sẽ viết phần data đó ra thiết bị, rồi return